{
    "question": "214)\uf020 The Indian Army conducted exercise named\n_________in the deserts of Rajasthan from\nNovember 29 to December 4",
    "answer": " Sindhu Sudarshan\n"
}{
    "question": "215)\uf020 Sangai is a popular cultural state festival of which\nstate",
    "answer": " Manipur\n"
}{
    "question": "216)\uf020 Which National Day is observed on November 27\nto promote organ donation for those who are in\nneed of them and creating awareness for\nremoving the taboo around organ donation",
    "answer": "\nIndian Organ Donation Day\n"
}{
    "question": "217)\uf020 International Day for the elimination of violence\nagainst women is celebrated on which date",
    "answer": "\nNovember 25\n"
}{
    "question": "218)\uf020 Which day is celebrated to mark the birth\nanniversary of Dr. Verghese Kurien, promoter of\nIndia's most successful dairy enterprise - Amul",
    "answer": "\nNational Milk Day\n"
}{
    "question": "219)\uf020 National Milk Day is observed on which date",
    "answer": "\nNovember 26\n"
}{
    "question": "220)\uf020 Rafael Nadal won the Davis Cup title for the sixth\ntime for which country",
    "answer": " Spain\n"
}{
    "question": "221)\uf020 India celebrates which day to commemorate\nadoption of the constitution by the constituent\nassembly in 1949",
    "answer": " The Constitution Day,\nNovember 26\n"
}{
    "question": "222)\uf020 Fast Patrol Vessel \u2018Amrit Kaur\u2019 was recently\ninducted in which armed force of India",
    "answer": " Indian\nCoast Guard\n"
}{
    "question": "223)\uf020 The Union Cabinet approved the establishment of\nthe National Institute for Sowa-Rigpa in which\nplace",
    "answer": " Leh, Ladakh\n"
}{
    "question": "224)\uf020 The Sowa-Rigpa represents which traditional\ndiscipline of medicine",
    "answer": " Tibetan system of\nmedicine\n"
}{
    "question": "225)\uf020 Lieutenant Shivangi became the first female pilot\nto join Indian Navy on Dec 2. She will fly which\naircraft",
    "answer": " Dornier surveillance aircraft\n"
}{
    "question": "226)\uf020 As per the latest edition of the Global Terrorism\nIndex, _________ is the country worst affected by\nterrorism",
    "answer": " Afghanistan\n"
}{
    "question": "227)\uf020 What is the rank of India as per the latest edition\nof the Global Terrorism Index",
    "answer": " 7th\n"
}{
    "question": "228)\uf020 In which state recently more than 18,000\nmigratory birds died at Sambhar Lake",
    "answer": " Rajasthan\n"
}{
    "question": "229)\uf020 For what reasons bacteria Avian Botulism was in\nnews recently",
    "answer": " It was cause of death of\nmigratory birds in Rajasthan\n"
}{
    "question": "230)\uf020 Who has been named as the World Athlete of the\nYear 2019 by the World Athletics",
    "answer": " Eliud\nKipchoge\n"
}{
    "question": "231)\uf020 Eliud Kpichoge hails from which country",
    "answer": " Kenya\n"
}{
    "question": "232)\uf020 Kipchoge excels in which sport of Athletics",
    "answer": "\nMarathon\n"
}{
    "question": "233)\uf020 Who has been selected as the World Athlete of the\nYear \u2013 women 2019 by the World Athletics",
    "answer": "\nDalilah Muhammad\n"
}{
    "question": "234)\uf020 Dalilah Muhammad hails from which country",
    "answer": "\nUSA\n"
}{
    "question": "235)\uf020 Dalilah Muhammad excels in which sports of\nAthletics",
    "answer": " 400 m world champion\n"
}{
    "question": "236)\uf020 Oxford Dictionaries has named which world as its\n2019 Word of the Year",
    "answer": " Climate Emergency\n"
}{
    "question": "237)\uf020 Name the 16-year-old young environmental\nactivist from Sweden who has been awarded\nInternational Children's Peace Prize",
    "answer": " Greta\nThunberg\n"
}{
    "question": "238)\uf020 The International Film Festival of India (IFFI)\nheld in Panaji, Goa from Nov 20 to 28 was which\nnumber in series",
    "answer": " 50th\n"
}{
    "question": "239)\uf020 Name the renowned French film actor who was\nhonoured with the Lifetime Achievement Award\nin the festival",
    "answer": " Isabelle Huppert\n"
}{
    "question": "240)\uf020 Name the Indian movie icon who has been\nbestowed with the Icon of the Jubilee Award at\nthe IFFI",
    "answer": " Rajinikanth\n"
}{
    "question": "241)\uf020 The two-day annual Conference of Governors and\nLieutenant Governors was held in ___________ , New\nDelhi, on Nov 23 and 24",
    "answer": " Rashtrapati Bhavan\n"
}{
    "question": "242)\uf020 Who has been chosen as Person of the Year 2019\nby PETA (People for the Ethical Treatment of\nAnimals)",
    "answer": " Virat Kohli\n"
}{
    "question": "243)\uf020 Fortune's annual Business Person of the Year list\nis topped by which CEO",
    "answer": " Satya Nadela\n"
}{
    "question": "244)\uf020 ________ won the men's singles title at International\nTable Tennis Federation (ITTF) Challenge\nIndonesia Open 2019 Table Tennis tournament",
    "answer": "\nHarmeet Desai\n"
}{
    "question": "245)\uf020 __________ became the 1st country in the world to\nintroduce a new Typhoid Conjugate Vaccine\n(TCV)",
    "answer": " Pakistan\n"
}{
    "question": "246)\uf020 The green tea and white tea of which place were\nrecently granted a geographical indication (GI)\ntag",
    "answer": " Darjeeling (West Bengal)\nGYANM GENERAL AWARENESS \u2013FEBRUARY 2020 84\n"
}{
    "question": "247)\uf020 Government launched \u2018SAANS\u2019 (Social Awareness\nand Action to Neutralise Pneumonia Successfully)\ncampaign aimed at reducing child mortality due\nto pneumonia, from which state",
    "answer": " Gujarat\n"
}{
    "question": "248)\uf020 Government of India aims to achieve a target of\nreducing pneumonia deaths among children to\nless than _______ per 1000 live births by 2025",
    "answer": "\nThree\n"
}{
    "question": "249)\uf020 Who is the winner of this year\u2019s Indira Gandhi\nPrize for Peace, Disarmament and Development",
    "answer": "\nSir David Attenborough\n"
}{
    "question": "250)\uf020 What is the amount of cash award of Indira\nGandhi Prize",
    "answer": " Rs. 25 lakh\n"
}{
    "question": "251)\uf020 The Union Government has launched Bharatiya\nPoshan Krishi Kosh with what aim",
    "answer": " Reducing\nmalnutrition in India\n"
}{
    "question": "252)\uf020 Which union ministry promotes the celebrations\nof the Naturopathy Day on November 18",
    "answer": " The\nAyush Ministry\n"
}{
    "question": "253)\uf020 Which International Day is associated with 6th\nSustainable Development Goal of UNO that aims\nto ensure availability sanitation and water for all\nby 2030",
    "answer": " World Toilet Day , November 19\n"
}{
    "question": "254)\uf020 India celebrates Children\u2019s Day on Nov 14. On\nwhich date the Universal Children\u2019s Day is\ncelebrated",
    "answer": " November 20\n"
}{
    "question": "255)\uf020 India\u2019s first winter grade diesel sales center was\nopened in _________ region on November 7",
    "answer": "\nLadakh\n"
}{
    "question": "256)\uf020 Which oil company has developed India\u2019s first\nWinter Grade Diesel",
    "answer": " Indian Oil Corporation\n"
}{
    "question": "257)\uf020 Who has been elected as the new President of Sri\nLanka",
    "answer": " Gotabaya Rajapaksa\n"
}{
    "question": "258)\uf020 What is the name of the national official body that\nfunctions as a moral watch dog to improve the\nstandards of journalism and maintain its\nfreedom",
    "answer": " Press Council of India\n"
}{
    "question": "259)\uf020 Which national day is celebrated to\ncommemorate the foundation of Press Council of\nIndia on November 16, 1966",
    "answer": " The National\nPress Day\n"
}{
    "question": "260)\uf020 Name the Indian star female sprinter who has\nbeen included in the \u2018Time 100 Next\u2019 list that\nincludes those who are ready to make future in\nbusiness, recreation, sports, politics, health and\nscience",
    "answer": " Dutee Chand\n"
}{
    "question": "261)\uf020 India\u2019s Ravi Prakash won the $25,000 BRICSYoung Innovator prize for which achievement",
    "answer": "\nFor the invention of the small and cheap 'Milk\nChilling Unit' useful for small and\neconomically weaker farmers\n"
}{
    "question": "262)\uf020 What was the theme of the 11th BRICS Summit in\nBrasilia",
    "answer": " Economic Growth for an Innovative\nFuture\n"
}{
    "question": "263)\uf020 President of which country has accepted our\ninvitation to be the Chief Guest at the Republic\nDay parade of 2020",
    "answer": " Brazil\n"
}{
    "question": "264)\uf020 Who is the President of Brazil",
    "answer": " Jair Bolsonaro\n"
}{
    "question": "265)\uf020 The 39th India International Trade Fair 2019 was\nheld in___________, New Delhi from Nov 14 to 27",
    "answer": "\nPragati Maidan\n"
}{
    "question": "266)\uf020 __________ was the partner country for this year\u2019s\nIndia International Trade Fair",
    "answer": " Afghanistan\n"
}{
    "question": "267)\uf020 __________ was the focus country for this year\u2019s\nIndia International Trade Fair",
    "answer": " South Korea\n"
}{
    "question": "268)\uf020 Which two Indian states were named as the focus\nstates for this year\u2019s India International Trade\nFair",
    "answer": " Bihar and Jharkhand\n"
}{
    "question": "269)\uf020 If you want to see Suranga Bawadi (mini pond),\nthe \u2018Ancient Water System of the Deccan Plateau\u2019,\nwhich place will you have to visit",
    "answer": " Bijapur,\nKarnataka\n"
}{
    "question": "270)\uf020 For what reasons Suranga Bawadi was in news\nrecently",
    "answer": " It has been selected in the World\nMonument Watch List for 2020\n"
}{
    "question": "271)\uf020 Swachh \u2013 Nirmal Tat (\u0924\u091f) Abhiyaan has been\nlaunched for what purpose",
    "answer": " To create\nawareness amongst citizens about the\nimportance of coastal ecosystems\n"
}{
    "question": "272)\uf020 Which online retailer company launched \"Project\nZero\" in India to ensure that customers receive\nauthentic goods when shopping on its website",
    "answer": "\nAmazon\n"
}{
    "question": "273)\uf020 The five-judge constitution bench of the Supreme\nCourt recently pronounced its landmark historical\njudgment on Right to Information Act. What was\nit",
    "answer": " It held that the Chief Justice of India's office\nis a public authority and hence comes under\nthe RTI Act\n"
}{
    "question": "274)\uf020 Which Indian state gave its approval for setting\nup of the world\u2019s first CNG (Compressed Natural\nGas) terminal at Bhavnagar port",
    "answer": " Gujarat\n"
}{
    "question": "275)\uf020 The International Hockey Federation has\nannounced that ________ will host the 2023 Men's\nHockey World Cup from 13th to 29th of January,\n2023",
    "answer": " India\nGYANM GENERAL AWARENESS \u2013FEBRUARY 2020 85\n"
}{
    "question": "276)\uf020 Sundar Singh Gurjar won gold in _______ in World\nPara Athletics Championships held in Dubai",
    "answer": "\nJavelin throw\n"
}{
    "question": "277)\uf020 ___________ 15 year-old girl from Rohtak, Haryana\nbecame the youngest (15 years, 285 days) Indian\ncricketer ever to score a half-century in\ninternational cricket",
    "answer": " Shafali Verma\n"
}{
    "question": "278)\uf020 The much talked about \u201cKartarpur Corridor\u201d\nconnects Dera Baba Nanak in district Gurdaspur\nto holy shrine in _________________ Narowal,\nPakistan",
    "answer": " Gurudwara Darbar Sahib, Kartapur\n"
}{
    "question": "279)\uf020 What is the historical importance of the\nGurudwara Sri Darbar Sahib",
    "answer": " This is the place\nwhere Guru Nanak Dev Ji breathed his last\n"
}{
    "question": "280)\uf020 The main celebrations of the Sri Guru Nanak Dev\nji on his 550th birth anniversary were held in\nSultanpur Lodhi. What is its historical\nimportance",
    "answer": " This is the place where Guru Ji\nstayed for many years and attained\nenlightenment\n"
}{
    "question": "281)\uf020 Cyclone \u2018Bulbul\u2019, the tropical storm devastated the\ncoastal districts of which state before hurtling\ntowards Bangladesh",
    "answer": " West Bengal\n"
}{
    "question": "282)\uf020 Name the former Chief Election Commissioner\nwho transformed the face of electoral process in\nthe country by introduction and strict\nimplementation of Voter ID Card",
    "answer": " T N Seshan\n"
}{
    "question": "283)\uf020 Sandeep Chaudhary and Sumit broke the world\nrecords on their way to winning the gold and\nsilver medals, respectively, in the ___________ event\nof the World Para Athletics Championships held\nat Dubai",
    "answer": " F64 javelin throw\n"
}{
    "question": "284)\uf020 India\u2019s MMR declined by 8 points in one year from\n130 per lakh live births in 2014-16 to 122 per\nlakh live births in 2015-17. What is MMR",
    "answer": "\nMaternal Mortality Rate\n"
}{
    "question": "285)\uf020 India recently launched the SUMAN programme\nfor moving towards zero preventable maternal\nand newborn deaths. Expand the term SUMAN",
    "answer": "\nSurakshit Matritva Aashwasan\n"
}{
    "question": "286)\uf020 Who is the author of the famous novel \u2018Swami and\nFriends\u2019",
    "answer": " R K Narayan\n"
}{
    "question": "287)\uf020 \u201cA Suitable Boy\u201d is a popular novel written by\nwhich author",
    "answer": " Vikram Seth\n"
}{
    "question": "288)\uf020 November 7 is observed as National Cancer\nAwareness Day. It happens to be the birthday of a\ngreat scientist whose research was very helpful in\nthe treatment of tumors and cancer. Can you\nname her",
    "answer": " Marie Curie\n"
}{
    "question": "289)\uf020 These days we hear a lot about nuisance of Parali\nburning in print and electronic media. What is\nParali",
    "answer": " Stubble of paddy left after harvesting\n"
}{
    "question": "290)\uf020 India has decided to opt out of which mega freetrade agreement recently",
    "answer": " RCEP\n"
}{
    "question": "291)\uf020 What is the full form of RCEP",
    "answer": " Regional\nComprehensive Economic Partnership\n"
}{
    "question": "292)\uf020 The National Green Tribunal (NGT) has ruled\nagainst the usage of RO (reverse osmosis)\nsystems, mainly for what reason",
    "answer": " It results in\nwastage of almost 80% of water\n"
}{
    "question": "293)\uf020 In which city Indian Railways has installed two\n\u2018Health ATMs\u2019 at the Charbagh railway station",
    "answer": "\nLucknow, UP\n"
}{
    "question": "294)\uf020 __________ became the first Indian cricketer to play\n100 T20 International cricket matches",
    "answer": " Rohit\nSharma\n"
}{
    "question": "295)\uf020 Raja Ram Mohan Roy award is conferred for\nrecognizing outstanding contribution in which\nfield",
    "answer": " Journalism\n"
}{
    "question": "296)\uf020 The central government has issued an HS Code for\nKhadi for what purpose",
    "answer": " To categorize its\nproducts exclusively in exports\n"
}{
    "question": "297)\uf020 What is the full form of HS Code",
    "answer": " Harmonized\nSystem\n"
}{
    "question": "298)\uf020 Which country\u2019s first-ever satellite, SRSS-1, was\nlaunched by China on November 3 from Shanxi\nProvince in north China",
    "answer": " Sudan\n"
}{
    "question": "299)\uf020 Maisnam Meiraba Luwang, 16 year old boy from\nManipur clinched the boys\u2019 singles U-19 title at\nthe Woncheon Yonex Korea Junior Open ______\nInternational Challenge 2019 in Miryang, Korea",
    "answer": "\nBadminton\n"
}{
    "question": "300)\uf020 Which organization recently introduced India\u2019s\nfirst nanotechnology-based fertiliser product\nrange by introducing Nano Nitrogen, Nano Zinc,\nNano Copper",
    "answer": " Indian Farmers Fertiliser\nCooperative Limited (IFFCO)\n"
}{
    "question": "301)\uf020 Which state launched a first of its kind job\nhelpline number 76260-76260 for the\nunemployed youth of the state under \u2018Ghar Ghar\nRozgar\u2019 programme",
    "answer": " Punjab\n"
}{
    "question": "302)\uf020 According to an estimate by the International\nMonetary Fund (IMF), which country\u2019s GDP is\nexpected to explode by growing at 86% in 2020",
    "answer": "\nGuyana\n"
}{
    "question": "303)\uf020 Which development is the factor behind expected\n86% growth of GDP in Guyana",
    "answer": " Discovery of vast \nGYANM GENERAL AWARENESS \u2013FEBRUARY 2020 86\noil resources\n"
}{
    "question": "304)\uf020 Which spacecraft of NASA entered the interstellar\nmedium (ISM) in space on November 05",
    "answer": "\nVoyager - 2\n"
}{
    "question": "305)\uf020 Ministry of Finance released two new IT\nInitiatives named ICEDASH and ATITHI to\nimprove monitoring and pace of which item",
    "answer": "\nCustoms clearance of imported goods and\nfacilitating arriving international passengers\n"
}{
    "question": "306)\uf020 The High-Level Advisory Group has\nrecommended the central government to launch\n______ Bonds to bring back $500 billion black\nmoney",
    "answer": " Elephant\n"
}{
    "question": "307)\uf020 The Indian Air Force has decided to retire its old\nwar horse - ________ strike aircraft on December 31\nthis year",
    "answer": " MiG-27\n"
}{
    "question": "308)\uf020 India received MiG-27 fighter aircrafts from\nwhich country",
    "answer": " Russia\n"
}{
    "question": "309)\uf020 The phaseout ceremony for the last fleet of MiG27 was held at which airbase",
    "answer": " Jodhpur,\nRajasthan\n"
}{
    "question": "310)\uf020 3rd Rugby World Cup was hosted by which city in\nJapan",
    "answer": " Yokohama\n"
}{
    "question": "311)\uf020 Which country lifted the 3rd Rugby World Cup",
    "answer": "\nSouth Africa\n"
}{
    "question": "312)\uf020 What is the popular name of the Rugby World\nCup",
    "answer": " Webb Ellis Cup\n"
}{
    "question": "313)\uf020 \u2018Chhath Puja\u2019 is one of the most popular festivals\nof which state",
    "answer": " Bihar\n"
}{
    "question": "314)\uf020 In Chhath Puja, devotees offer their prayers to\nand seek blessings from which God",
    "answer": " Sun\n"
}{
    "question": "315)\uf020 ___________ has become the first state in the country\nto enact a law on contract farming",
    "answer": " Tamil Nadu\n"
}{
    "question": "316)\uf020 Researchers from which apex IT institute have\ncreated the first-ever \u2018Indian Brain Atlas\u2019",
    "answer": " Indian\nInstitute of Information Technology\nHyderabad (IIIT-H), Telangana\n"
}{
    "question": "317)\uf020 Which two Indian cities have been selected as a\nmember of UNESCO Creative Cities Network",
    "answer": "\nMumbai and Hyderabad\n"
}{
    "question": "318)\uf020 Mumbai and Hyderabad have been selected as a\nmember of UNESCO Creative Cities Network in\nwhich fields",
    "answer": " Films and Gastronomy,\nrespectively\n"
}{
    "question": "319)\uf020 The Heads of government summit of the Shanghai\nCooperation Organisation (SCO) was held in\nwhich city from November 1-3",
    "answer": " Tashkent\n"
}{
    "question": "320)\uf020 Tashkent is capital of which country",
    "answer": " Uzbekistan\n"
}{
    "question": "321)\uf020 Which university in UK has established a New\nGuru Nanak Chair to mark the 550th Birth\nAnniversary of Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
    "answer": " University of\nBirmingham\n"
}{
    "question": "322)\uf020 The 35th ASEAN Summit was held in which place\nin Thailand from Oct 31 to Nov 4",
    "answer": " Bangkok\n"
}{
    "question": "323)\uf020 ASEAN is a group of how many countries",
    "answer": " 10\n"
}{
    "question": "324)\uf020 Vyas Samman is associated with outstanding\nperformance in which field",
    "answer": " Hindi Literature\n"
}{
    "question": "325)\uf020 Name the renowned Hindi author who was\nconferred Vyas Samman 2018 recently",
    "answer": "\nLeeladhar Jagoori\n"
}{
    "question": "326)\uf020 Sh. Leeladhar Jagoori won the Vyas Samman 2018\nfor his which work",
    "answer": " Poetry collection- \u201cJitne\nLog Utne Prem\u201d.\n"
}{
    "question": "327)\uf020 Former Parliamentarian and veteran CPI\n(Communist Party of India) leader, Gurudas\nDadgupta was in news recently for what reasons",
    "answer": "\nHe breathed his last\n"
}{
    "question": "328)\uf020 The CBSE and NCERT launched the only aptitude\ncalled TAMANNA. What is its full form",
    "answer": " Try And\nMeasure Aptitude And Natural Abilities\n"
}{
    "question": "329)\uf020 The TAMANNA programme aims to help students\nof which class to make a better selection of\nsubjects",
    "answer": " 9th and 10th\n"
}{
    "question": "330)\uf020 Two Central Public Sector Enterprises (CPSEs),\nhave been granted \u2018Maharatna\u2019 status by the\nGovernment. What is their name",
    "answer": " Hindustan\nPetroleum Corporation Ltd. and Power Grid\nCorporation of India Ltd.\n"
}{
    "question": "331)\uf020 Name the Nepali mountaineer who has become\nthe fastest mountain climber as he scaled 14\nhighest peaks, all over 8,000 mts, in just over six\nmonths",
    "answer": " Nirmal Purja\n"
}{
    "question": "332)\uf020 Who has been appointed as the 47th Chief Justice\nof India",
    "answer": " Justice Sharad Arvind Bobde\nOCTOBER 2019\n"
}